<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Providence bringing good out of evil in a sermon, preached on the ninth of September, being the day of thanksgiving for the discovery of the late treasonable conspiracy against His Majesties person and government / by Richard Pearson ...</title>
            <author>Pearson, Richard, d. 1734.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53906</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1014</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20743</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12610738</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12610738</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64352</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53906)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64352)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 771:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Providence bringing good out of evil in a sermon, preached on the ninth of September, being the day of thanksgiving for the discovery of the late treasonable conspiracy against His Majesties person and government / by Richard Pearson ...</title>
                  <author>Pearson, Richard, d. 1734.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.M. and J.A. for Henry Bonwicke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 42.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXVI, 10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64352:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64352:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PROVIDENCE Bringing <hi>Good out of Evil,</hi> IN A SERMON, PREACHED On the Ninth of <hi>September,</hi> being the Day of Thankſgiving for the Diſcovery of the late Treaſonable Conſpiracy againſt His Majeſties Perſon and Government.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD PEARSON,</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Michaels Crooked-Lane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. M.</hi> and <hi>J. A.</hi> for <hi>Henry Bonwicke,</hi> at the <hi>Red-Lyon,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:64352:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64352:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. LXXVI. 10.</bibl>
               <q>Surely the Wrath of Man ſhall Praiſe Thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHoever was the Author of this <hi>Pſalm</hi> (which ſeems to have been Compoſed, not by <hi>David,</hi> but ſome other Holy Writer after his time) or to whatſoever particular Hiſtory it may more immediately relate; thus much is however moſt certain, from the very Genius and Contexture of the <hi>Pſalm,</hi> that the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of its Compoſure was ſome ſignal Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and remarkable Deliverance, by which God was pleaſed to reſcue his People out of the hands of their Powerful Enemies; and that it was Penned alſo for the ſtanding Uſe and Comfort of God's Church, in all ſuch Circumſtances. And accordingly, after the Divine Author has Magnifi'd God's wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Power and Wiſdom from the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his ſo remarkable reſcue of his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64352:3"/> People, in that particular Defeat of their Enemies, he falls at laſt upon this general Concluſion here in my Text; <hi>Surely the wrath of Man ſhall Praiſe. Thee</hi>—</p>
            <p>From which Words I ſhall take occaſion to doe theſe two Things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall conſider the Truth of the Propoſition, and what ſufficient Grounds we have to be aſſured in the General, that all the outragious Actions of wicked and ungodly Men, are by that Over-ruling Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence which knows how to bring Good out of Evil, conſtantly forced (quite contrary to the deſigns and intents of the Perſons ſo Acting) towards the accidental Promotion of God's Glory, and the good of his Church. I ſhall endeavour to ſhew Breifly, what ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient grounds of Reaſon we have to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of this in the General, even though we had no ſuch clear Examples of the thing, nor were able to give any account of the particular manner how this ſhould come to paſs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For our more abundant ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in ſo comfortable a Truth, I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, by the help of Scripture, more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to demonſtrate ſome of the cheif ways
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64352:3"/> and manners how the outragious actions and wicked enterpriſes of the Enemies of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion are at laſt forced to turn to God's Praiſe, and the real Benefit of his faithful People.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I am to conſider the Truth of the Propoſition, and what ſufficient grounds we have to be aſſured of this in the general, though we had no clear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Examples of the thing, nor were able to give any account of the particular manner how this ſhould come to paſs. That it is, that it muſt be ſo in the general, and cannot be otherwiſe, we have as much, we have the ſame Reaſon to be certain of, as we have that there is a God who Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns the World, a Supreme abſolutely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Beeing that Rules and Diſpoſes all Events ſo as is moſt agreeable to ſuch the Eſſential Perfection of his Nature. So that as ſure as God is Infinitely Wiſe, and therefore infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly knows what will, and what will not, make for his own Glory and the good of his Church; as ſure as he is Infinitely Good and holy, and ſo willing to promote the ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as ſure as he is Infinitely powerful, ſo that he can eaſily bring about whatſoever he deſires, and not onely hinder but perfectly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64352:4"/> annihilate whatever other Beeing goes to reſiſt him? no leſs ſure is it, that neither Man nor Devil (let their Malice and curſed Purpoſes be what they will) are ever ſuffered to proceed to outward Act, to put any thing in Execution, but only what God can and does ſo Over-rule by his Providence, as that it ſhall be ſubſervient to his own Holy and Wiſe ends, and be actually made uſe of by him, ſooner or later, ſo as to turn to his Glory, and the real advantage of his faithful Servants. Very remarkable to this purpoſe is that great ſaying of St. <hi>Auguſtin;</hi> God, who is the Supream Governour and diſpoſer of all things, would by no means ſuffer any Evil to be in the World, were he not ſo In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely Wiſe and Good and Powerful as to make Evil it ſelf become beneficial, by bringing good out of it. God's Infinite Power and Providence Over-rules and ſets Bounds to the Rage of the Devil and all his wicked Inſtruments; ſo that while they Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute and Deſigne utterly to deſtroy God's People, and though ſeveral of Chriſt's Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers may, for the preſent, ſuffer under their Rage, God in his Infinite Wiſdom ſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains them, that they can go no farther
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64352:4"/> than accidentally tends to the real advantage of his Church in general. They build up and ſtrengthen what they would deſtroy; their own deſigns contradict and recoil upon themſelves, and, in the event, defeat their own Intentions. The Devil himſelf is forced, againſt his will, to doe God's Work, and to promote his Glory, while he intends nothing leſs. The Rage of Man turns to God's Praiſe, and as for the remainder of wrath which would not do ſo, which cannot be made uſe of nor converted to this purpoſe, God is ſure always to reſtrain it, and never ſuffers it to take effect by putting its deſigns in Execution. Howſoever unprofitable or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive the wicked actions of Men may be to themſelves who commit them, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever immediatly offenſive to God and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Will the irregularity and immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the ſame is; yet when the thing is done, God is ſure to make ſome good uſe of it, and to have his own Will out of the very worſt action that Men commit, and would not otherwiſe ever permit it to be done. It's impoſſible indeed, that we poor, weak, finite Creatures ſhould be able, in a Thouſand Inſtances of this Nature, to diſcover the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64352:5"/> particular manner how this ſhould be brought about: but God ſees not as Man ſees; he beholds things at once and together; he is perfectly well acquainted with all the ſeveral circumſtances, connexion, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendences of things upon each other. He ſees what will be the laſt end of ſuch or ſuch an Adverſary; what influence the alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations he is permitted to work will have, and upon what Perſons, and how far diſtant; how many Years, or (ſometimes) Ages af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the benefit will accrue. Of all this now, and a Thouſand other Circumſtances we are wholy ignorant and unable to conſider. So that we muſt needs be much to ſeek concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the particular manner how God will bring Good out of ſuch an Evil; but yet that he will do ſo in the general, we can no more queſtion, than we can doubt of God's Goodneſs, Omniſcience and Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; that is, whether there be indeed a God. If we be ſatisfied of this, we ſhall alſo find Reaſon to conclude, <hi>That all things</hi> (that is, all Afflictions and Perſecutions, which are the effects of other Mens Wrath) <hi>ſhall work together for good to them that love God;</hi> and that the Wrath of Man ſhall turn to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64352:5"/> Gods Praiſe, though we were not furniſhed with ſo many Examples of the thing, nor were enabled to give any account at all, concerning the manner how this ſhould be brought to paſs.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, For our more abundant ſatisfaction in ſo comfortable a Truth, I ſhall, in the next place, endeavour more particularly to domonſtrate ſome of the cheif ways and ſeveral manners how the outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Actions and wicked enterpriſes of the Enemies of Religion are, at laſt, forced to turn to the Divine Praiſe, and the real benefit of God's faithful People.</p>
            <p>And this may come to paſs, Firſt, As ſuch ruggid dealings with them, tends more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to antidote them from being tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and infected with the Errours and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of ſuch Enemies. For, ſhould wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men and falſe Worſhippers, ceaſing to Perſecute the true Profeſſours, allow them fair quarter, and behave themſelves kindly and courteouſly towards them, there would then be far more danger of their being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and enticed to partake of the ſame Abominations, and to enter upon ſuch a familiarity as might prove very deſtructive,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64352:6"/> and of the worſt conſequence. But now, the many injuries and ill turns which the Enemies of the Truth do uſually offer to the Godly, That Rage againſt them, and Hatred, which they are ready upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions to ſhew, is generally in it ſelf, a very powerful ſecurity from the former danger. And this may be (among many others) one good Reaſon why God is pleaſed to permit thoſe that are born after the Fleſh, to malign, and Perſecute thoſe that are born after the Spirit, <hi>viz.</hi> that thereby, they might be free from the many Temptations and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of ſeduction, which might attend a familiarity with ſuch Men: and be leſs ſubject to take the Infection of their Errours and bad Examples; ſo that if no other good did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally come to us, from the Rage of ſuch Men, this is certainly to be lookt upon as no ſmall advantage.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, The Rage of ſuch Perſons is forced to turn to God's Praiſe, as Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions tend to correct the failings of good Men, and to exerciſe and illuſtrate their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Graces and Virtues. By theſe, good Men are uſually made much better and more approved, while they tend to exerciſe our
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64352:6"/> Patience, to quicken our Devotion, to Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence our Zeal and Chriſtian Fortitude, and to ſhew to the whole World what Love we bear to the Truth, and how much we are willing to undergo for the Honour of God. Till they have ſuffered ſomething for it. Truth is too apt to grow Cheap and be leſs priz'd ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, even by thoſe that are good Men, for the main; whereas we are Apt on the contrary, never to value it at a higher Rate, or to be more Zealous for it, or to make better uſe of it, than when it is oppoſed and perſecuted. What more truly Beneficial therefore or tending to the Divine Glory, than for God, Who uſeth to bring Good out of Evil, To make uſe alſo of the Oppoſers of his Truth, to Rouſe up his Servants, whom he ſees growing more Remiſs and Negligent than they ſhould be and to Suffer ſuch Temptations to aſſalt them, by which their Drouſie Minds may be Spurred on into a greater Love and Zeal for the Truth, and a deeper Senſe of the Divine Benefit in it; and in general, Excited to the more Diligent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of their Duty. In ſhort, ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able are Men generally to bear long proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, without being the worſe for it, and of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64352:7"/> ſuch Excellent uſe is Adverſity to Purge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ill Humours, which the beſt Men are too Apt to contract, that God ſees it highly convenient, for the general good of his Servants, ſometimes to make uſe of this Method; and does therefore ever and anon, within ſome few Ages, permit ill Men to become the Rods and Inſtruments of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to his People, and uſe them as Prun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Hooks in his Vineyard.</p>
            <p>Outward Trials and Adverſities do uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moſt of all promote the true inward Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Proſperity of God's Church. Nor does any thing conduce more, either to reſtore it, or to keep it Sound and in Health, than the due Exerciſes and Breathings of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I ſhall Conclude this particular, with that Notable paſſage of St. <hi>Hirom,</hi> who in one of his Books has theſe Words; <hi>Scribere diſpoſui, ſi tamen Dominus vitam dederit,</hi> &amp;c. I determine with my ſelf, (if God ſhall give me Life) to write a Hiſtory from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Saviour, to our preſent Times; that is, from the Times of the Apoſtles to the Dregs of this Age; in which I deſign to ſhew at large, how, and by whom the Church of God was Repliniſhed; how it was ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64352:7"/> by Perſecutions, and crowned by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdoms; and when it came to Chriſtian Princes, How ſtrangely it was diminiſhed in Virtue, while it encreaſed in Riches and Eaſe, in External Power and Proſperity.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Another manner after which the Wrath of Man is forced to turn to God's Praiſe is, when he makes the very Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Malice of Wicked Men againſt his Servants, become the Effectual means, or occaſion of promoting their welfair, and of bringing about that very good thing, which the other deſired and deſigned, thereby, to hinder. And now, as there are few good Men, I'm perſwaded, who diligently obſerve and take Notice of God's Providential dealings and wiſe diſpoſal of Things, but can readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find ſome happy Inſtances of this, in their own Experience, either in Relation to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or ſome other of their acquaintance; ſo ſhall we not fail (however) of meeting with variety of Examples of this kind, in Holy Scripture. Thus while the Envy and Malice of <hi>Joſephs</hi> Bretheren moved them to ſell him to the <hi>Iſhmaelites,</hi> out of a deſign to prevent and hinder that Exaltation of his, which had been ſignified to him in a Dream,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64352:8"/> God was pleaſed, in his wonderful Providence, ſo to order all Circumſtances, as that they thereby put him into the direct Rode of his Preferment, and far more Effectually (tho Ignorantly indeed and full contrary to their own Will) contributed thereto, than if they had all laid their Heads together and Studied moſt induſtriouſly how to Effect the ſame. And accordingly <hi>Joſeph</hi> was ſo thorowly Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of Gods Over-ruling Providence and Gracious deſign, from the very firſt, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them to put their Wicked deſign in Execution, that he calls their Selling of him by the Name of Gods ſending him into <hi>Egypt Gen.</hi> 45. 5. Be not Angry with your ſelves, that you Sold me; For God ſent me before you, to preſerve Life. And <hi>Gen.</hi> 50. 20. As for you, you thought Evil againſt me, but God meant it unto Good. And thus alſo whilſt Wicked <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> contriving how to hinder the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from ſo Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying and growing ſo mighty, as that they might at laſt depart from him, by a ſtrong Hand, and caſt off the Yoak from them, Commands his People to caſt all the Male-Children of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> into the River, God was pleaſed to make uſe of this very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64352:8"/> of the Bloudy Tyrant, as the Happy means and occaſion, not only of <hi>Moſes</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and Preferment, but alſo of the whole peoples Deliverance. For, with him, in an Ark of Bul-Ruſhes, Swims alſo the whole Fortune of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and certainly Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives at a ſafe Harbour. And little did <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> think that this Command of his <hi>ſhould prove</hi> an Effectual Recommendation of that very Perſon to the <hi>Care</hi> of his own Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Daughter, and help him to the Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his own Court, who ſhould there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be better prepared and qualified to become the Prince and Leader of the People <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and prove at laſt the happy Inſtrument to Effect that Deliverance, which the Tyrant endeavoured ſo much to prevent. And ſo afterwards, though <hi>Pharaoh</hi> deſigned no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the ſecuring them to himſelf for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, by diſpiriting of that People, and keeping them under in the hardeſt Bondage; God was graciouſly pleaſed to permit this Oppreſſion for a while, as a good means (and perhaps the only Effectual one,) to prepare and make them willing to follow <hi>Moſes,</hi> and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Land of <hi>Egypt</hi> and thoſe Habitations, which long Time and Cuſtom had ſo much
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64352:9"/> endeared to them. And we may eaſily gueſs how very hardly they could ever have been perſwaded to have thought of any ſuch thing, had they but been ſuffered to enjoy any Tolerable Condition among the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> when, notwithſtanding all their former Extream hard uſage, and miraculous Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, and when, notwithſtanding their being Fed with moſt Delicious Manna in the Wilderneſs, and the hopes of Poſſeſſing a Land Flowing with Milk and Hony, they could yet, after all this, find in their Hearts to hanker after the Fleſh-Pots, and pine for the Garlick and Onyons of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and wiſh that they had Lived and Died there.</p>
            <p>But to proceed to other Inſtances; what can we think of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Envy and Rage againſt <hi>David,</hi> the many hazardous employments he put him upon, and the attempts he made to deſtrov and hinder him from Succeeding him? what were all theſe, but as ſo many ſeveral ſteps which providence made uſe of, to mount him to the Throne? while they ſerv'd effectually to make him both more gracious and renowned among the people, and more fit and better qualified to Reign ovre them. In ſhort, all <hi>Saul</hi>'s Rage againſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64352:9"/> him ſerved only to make a more ſpeedy way, for <hi>David,</hi> while the other ran furiouſly upon his own diſtruction, in oppoſing him.</p>
            <p>Again, how little did Saint <hi>Paul</hi> think, whileſt yet <hi>Saul,</hi> and breathing out Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and Perſecution againſt Chriſtians, that by permitting him ſo to Rage, God was fitting him to become a more Eminent Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the propagation of the Chriſtian Faith? and that his ſo Perſecuting ſhould afterwards prove a moſt effectual means to confirm and build up that Church which he deſigned, thereby, to deſtroy? And yet, is not the conſideration of ſo violent a Perſecutour, all of a ſudden, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into the ſtouteſt Champion, an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable Evidence of the reality of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Conviction, by Chriſts ſpeaking to him from Heaven; and ſo both enough, of it ſelf, to convince, or confound the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <hi>Jews</hi> then, and to be always a ſtanding irrefragable Argument, to all Poſterity that well conſider it, of the Truth and Divinity of the whole Chriſtian Religion in general? I ſhall give onely one Inſtance more of this kind, whereas I might be yet numerous. The greateſt wickedneſs that ever was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64352:10"/> by the Sons of Men, proved an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the greateſt glory to God, and of the moſt ſingular benefit that could befall Mankind. I need not tell you, that I mean the putting to Death of our bleſſed Saviour, towards the effecting of which, whilſt <hi>Judas</hi> was moved out of ſorded Covetouſneſs; the Scribes and Phariſes and cheif Prieſts, out of implacable Malice and Envy; <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> out of baſe Ambition and fear of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and others, to ſatisfie other vile ends of their own; God was pleaſed to permit all theſe ſinful motions of the ſeveral Perſons therein concerned, and to order ſuch a concurrence of circumſtances, as that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould hinder them from putting their wicked deſign in execution; God himſelf making uſe of them, as Inſtruments, for the effecting of his own moſt holy and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious purpoſes therein.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, (which ſeems alſo to be the moſt direct Meaning and Relation of my Text) The Wrath of Man turns, at laſt, to God's Praiſe, while it gives occaſion unto all of magnifying and admiring the Divine Power, Wiſdom and Goodneſs towards his Servants, in reſtraining the force of their Perſecutors;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64352:10"/> in wonderfully ſupporting and preſerving them under their Preſſures, and in his remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable Deliverances of them out of all their Dangers, by the total Defeat and Overthrow of their Adverſaries. Thus the Fury of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar,</hi> which cauſed the Furnace to be heated Seven times hotter than uſual, what did it elſe effect or ſerve for, but only to make God's Glory ſhine ſo much the brighter, in his Miraculous Preſervation of the Three Childeren? by which, as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Living Martyrs, ſo does the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſame, force the <hi>Haughty Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch</hi> to become himſelf a kind of Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour, and extort from him this Notable Magnificat and Acknowledgment, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 28. Then <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> ſpake and ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed be the God of</hi> Shadrach, Miſhach <hi>and</hi> Abednego, &amp;c. So while the Malitious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents endeavoured to deſtroy <hi>Daniel,</hi> by geting him caſt into the Den of Lions, what did they procure thereby, but the Prophets greater Exaltation and Favour with the King, and the utter Ruin of themſelves and their whole Families? And what an occaſion did it prove of God's being generally Glorified, while, in conſideration of the ſo Miraculous
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64352:11"/> Deliverance, King <hi>Darius</hi> makes this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Decree and Acknowledgment, <hi>Dan. 6. 26. That in every Dominion of his Kingdom, Men ſhould Tremble and Fear before the God of</hi> Daniel: <hi>for he is the Living God, and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Stedfaſt for ever, and his kingdom that which ſhall not be deſtroyed, and his Dominion ſhall be ever un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the End. He delivereth and reſcueth, and he worketh Signs and Wonders, in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and in Earth.</hi> I might alſo remind you of the Hiſtory of Proud <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence and Prodigious Obſtinacy had at laſt ſuch a Concluſion, and his in Rage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God's People procured him ſo Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous an over-throw, as that he was (though unwillingly) the occaſion of more Glory unto God, than, perhaps, any the moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Prince, by his greateſt Piety. I might alſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Inſtance in the Wonderful Defeat of <hi>Senacherib</hi>'s Numerous Army; which, as it was (probably) the occaſion of this Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant <hi>Pſalm</hi> in general, ſo may it ſerve like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as a ſtanding Monument of the Truth of my Text in particular. Which I might<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> have ſtill illuſtrated, by ſome farther conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations: but I proceed rather to a particular Application, in reference to the preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64352:11"/> In the Management of which I ſhall confine my ſelf to theſe Two Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals,</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall briefly conſider the Horrour and Hainouſneſs of that late Barbarous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, which the Helliſh Wrath and Fury of Phanatick Spirits engaged them to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, againſt the Life of our Dread Sovereign, and for the deſtruction of all his Faithful Adherents, their Bretheren and Fellow-Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, who were at quiet in the Land.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew how the Curſed Deſigns and Attempts of this their Rage againſt us, thus clearly diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Miraculouſly defeated, may Natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tend, by the Divine Grace and Bleſſing, to the Praiſe and Glory of God, and the real welfare and ſingular Benefit of this Church and Nation.</p>
            <p>As to the Firſt of theſe, In conſidering of this Conſpiracy, I ſhall not think it needful to go about to ſhew the certainty of the thing it ſelf; which has been ſo abundantly proved, by all ſorts of Evidence, that indeed nothing of this Nature is capable of more, or better; nor could there have been made a more clear Diſcovery or Confirmation, unleſs by the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64352:12"/> Actual Accompliſhment of ſo Damnable a Deſign. One of the Accomplices, out of meer Guilt and Horrour of Conſcience, lays Violent Hands upon himſelf; very many of the reſt Fly, as afraid to ſtand the Juſt Trial of our Laws; and thoſe who have been Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and Suffered for the Crime, have all of them confeſt the Thing, in General. In ſhort, there's no Man, I'm perſwaded, will pretend in the leaſt to queſtion or disbelieve it, but only ſuch Perſons, who themſelves full well know it to be true, and could alſo, if they pleaſed, give us their own Evidence in the Caſe. I cannot think it requiſite neither, that I ſhould much Act the part of an Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, by endeavouring to repreſent all the matter of Fact (ſo far as yet diſcovered) or give you a Compleat Scheme of the whole Contrivance, ſince this hath been done alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Sufficiently, by Reading to you the King's Declaration,</p>
            <p>I ſhall pretend no farther at preſent, but only breifly to remark, and Point out to you ſome few of the many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Aggravating Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of this Conſpiracy, and ſuch as are big with the fowleſt Deformity, the blackeſt Horrour and Ingratitude.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:64352:12"/>
            <p>And here I might firſt remark the Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Impudence of theſe vile Miſcreants, who were not aſhamed thus, in the ſame Age, and by the ſame Ways and Methods, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the Deſtruction of the Son, by which they had before Ruined his Father of ever Bleſſed Memory; that they ſhould ſo far Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front their own Reaſon, and bid ſuch defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to Heaven it ſelf, as to dare to deſign upon the Life, of a Prince ſo abundantly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned ſo ſignalized by the particular Care of Providence, ſo wonderfully Reſtored, ſo all along preſerved by almoſt a continued Series of Miracles. I might alſo remind you of the no leſs Monſtrous Ingratitude of theſe wicked Wretches, both toward God and His Sacred Majeſty. For ſeveral of the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> chief Conſpirators, were ſuch as had been raiſed to their Height, by His Majeſties ſpecial Favour and Bounty, ſuch upon whom he had heaped Honours, or Obliged by the greateſt Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits; and yet nothing was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> enough to Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their Greedy Covetuouſneſs and Ambition. And moſt of thoſe who were to be the main Inſtruments in this black Tragedy, were ſuch as had been in Arms<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo active in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Rebellion, as that they had long ago
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64352:13"/> received according to their Deſerts, had it not been for the wonderful Clemency of the Kings Act of Oblivion. And yet theſe ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled not, in requital, to deprive him of Life, who had ſo graciouſly given them their own.</p>
            <p>I might tell you how they firſt prepared the way for a general Rebellion, by beſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering and diſabling the Kings moſt Faithful Subjects, and repreſenting all his firm Friends under the Odious Character of Papiſts, and Popiſhly Affected; by raſing Tumults, Riots, and Sedition; by contiually ſending forth whole Swarms of the moſt falſe and Veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Libels; by every where ſpreading Fears and Jealouſies; by the moſt Malicious Lies and Slanders; by the moſt Horrid Perjuries and Subornations. In ſhort, by ſo Obſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the due Courſe of the Laws themſelves, and Debauching the Execution of them to their own vile purpoſes, through the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of ſome Officers, that Loyalty was made the only Crime to be puniſhed, and none ſo ſure to go free, and be applauded too, as thoſe who had made themſelves, in the higheſt manner, Obnoxius to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And when at laſt a ſtop was put to theſe proceedings, ſo that they perceived they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64352:13"/> could not, by theſe Methods, ſo ſpeedily Effect what they Deſigned; then they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive preſently how to Murder the King and his Royal Brother, after the moſt Barbarous manner, and to follow that with a General Maſſacre of all the moſt Loyal Nobility and Gentry of the Land. And, which ſtill height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens this Villany even to Aſtoniſhment, all theſe black Deſigns were underhand promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and carried on, by the pretence of Zeal for the Proteſtant Religion, under colour of Securing the Kings Perſon, and the Prevention of Popery and Arbitrary Government.</p>
            <p>Thus, had not God's Miraculous Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence prevented, when once the Fatal Blow had been ſtrucken, and all the King's Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Subjects Butchered, the Conſpiratours (of ſo different Parties and Opinions that nothing now Unites them, but their Common Hatred againſt, and deſire to deſtroy the preſent Government) would then moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have ſoon quarrel'd among themſelves, and a new Scene of Bloud and Confuſion have followed, till at laſt this miſerable Land weakened to ſo high a decree, with her own unnatural Convulſions, muſt in all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, have become an eaſie Prey to a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64352:14"/> Conquerour; and ſo that Popery and Slavery have been indeed Introduced, which theſe Men all along ſo much only pretended to Fear. For let ſuch Men talk what they will, I cannot think that they are really a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of Popery; but are glad only to Create, and then manage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and promote the Fears of it, in order to the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Diſtruction of our Eſtabliſhed Religion and Government; which they ſeem to hate far worſe than Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it ſelf. As to their Loyalty towards Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I'm ſure, ther's no great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Principles of a Phanatick, and of a Jeſuit. They are both well enough agreed about the thing it ſelf, and Quarrel only, which of them ſhould have the ſole priviledg of Murdering Princes. And in this laſt Plot, they thought (as 'tis uſual ſaid) to wrong the very Devil; and have indeed thereby made themſelves far worſe than the very worſt Papiſts, by deſigning to Murther the King themſelves, and then to caſt it, and pretend to revenge it, upon them, and all thoſe they ſhould think fit to brand with that Character. By which unparallel'd Villany, they ſeem, at laſt, to have found out a new Expedient, to Rid this Land of Jeſuits; who may now
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64352:14"/> think themſelves ſo perfectly out done in their own Trade, as, perhaps, out of meer ſhame and diſpare of ever equalizing theſe, they may reſolve to ſhew their Heads here no more. But however, let them do what they pleaſe; this Conſpiracy is, in it ſelf, ſuch a Maſter-Peice of all Iniquity, ſuch a Monſtrous Complication of the greateſt Villany, as cannot but Aſtoniſh all thoſe who conſider it, at preſent, and will, perhaps, ſcarcely gain Credit with Poſterity, that ever any Humane Creatures ſhould be capable of ſuch Degeneracy from their Nature. In the mean time, it is to be hoped, that the ſame God, (whoſe Infinite Wiſdom uſeth to bring Good out of Evil, and who has been pleaſed, in greateſt Mercy, to prevent ſo ſad Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation) will alſo turn the Diſcovery of this Plot, to his own Glory, and the laſting Peace and Security of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Which brings me now to the Second Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral thing I was to endeavour to ſhew, <hi>viz.</hi> How, the Curſed Deſigns and Attempts of this their Rage againſt us, thus clearly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and Miraculouſly defeated, may Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally tend, by the Divine Grace and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, to the Praiſe and Glory of God, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64352:15"/> to the Real Welfare, and Singular Benefit, of this Church and Nation.</p>
            <p>And to this Excellent purpoſe now, it tends, as it may Juſtly ſerve, to ſtrike Terrour and Confuſion into the Hearts of all thoſe who have been any ways concerned in, or Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Promotors of this Unnatural Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy; who may well be moved, from hence, with deepeſt Shame and Sorrow, to conſider and reflect upon what they have done; what extream Folly and Madneſs they have been guilty of; and forever be deterred, for the future, from undertaking or engaging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in any ſuch wicked Enterprize. Whilſt, from the Conſideration of the ſo remarkable Detection and Baffle of their Deſigns, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Juſt and Exemplary Puniſhment of ſeveral of their Fellow-Criminals, they are Furniſhed with a moſt ſenſible Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument and Demonſtration of the Vanity of ſuch Attempts, and what a tender Care and watchful Eye, Providence has for the Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Preſervation of his own Vice-ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; ſo that the Counſels and Attempts of ſuch as go about to Violate the Perſons of their Lawful Princes and Governours, are Commonly Vain and Inſuccesful; their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64352:15"/> Wrath proves, at laſt, Impotent, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive only to themſelves; they do but Fight againſt God himſelf, in <hi>diviſing how to put him out whom God will Exalt.</hi> And indeed, our preſent Sovereign has been ſo often and remarkably preſerved, and, from this laſt Conſpiracy, by ſuch an Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and (almoſt) Unparallel'd Inſtance of the Divine Providence, that it may ſeem hard even for the moſt <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> Spirit, not to be Convinced thereby; and ſhould be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſtrike ſuch an Awe into the Minds of all thoſe who have any remaining Sparks of Religion, or the leaſt Suſpition of a Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that, for the time to come, one would think it ſhould be altogether as Impoſſible to find any willing to Attempt, as it has proved hitherto to Effect, His Deſtruction. And this very Conſideration of God's ſo Wonderfully interpoſing to blaſt their Helliſh Plot, Juſt when they had made all ſo ſure, that in all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Judgment, it was Impoſſible for them to fail of Effecting it, had ſuch a ſtrange Influence upon the mind of one of the Conſpirators, that (according to his own Confeſſion) he was ready to relent, and give over thereupon. Nor could he have prevailed with himſelf to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64352:16"/> have gon on, againſt ſuch a Flaming Sword as ſtood in the way to deter him, had it not been for the Company and Encouragement of a far more falſe and wicked Prophet than <hi>Balaam,</hi> who ſo Thirſted after Royal Bloud, and the Rewards of Unrighteouſneſs, that he could neither<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſee nor hear any thing, but ſoon ſtopt the Mouth of his Creature that talkt to him of going back, and Spurred him on again, by a moſt Impious and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptious Miſinterpretation of that Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Providence, which ought to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred them.</p>
            <p>If ſuch true Proteſtants had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but as much Religion as the great <hi>Turk</hi> (whoſe cauſe they ſo much Favour at preſent, and wiſh for his Succeſs againſt Chriſtians) they would, from the conſideration of God's ſo ſtrange and remarkable Deliverances of our King, Learn, if not (as 'tis ſaid that <hi>Barbarian</hi> does) to Entertain a high eſteem of his Majeſty; yet at leaſt out of mere diſpair of Succeſs, (eſpecially after this laſt Defeat,) to be afraid to think any more of lifting up their Hands<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> againſt Him. Treaſon, I confeſs, has in it ſuch a Complication of other greivous Sins, and the main Contrivers and chief Agitators<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:64352:16"/> of it, have uſually ſuch ſtrangely Debauched Underſtandings, and Hardened Hearts, by a long Cuſtom in other Sins againſt Conſcience, that though, through the Prince's Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, they Eſcape and be Pardoned again and again; yet they ſeldom truly Repent, or leave off their Diſloyal Practices; ſcarce any Defeats are Sufficient to Diſcourage them; but ſtill, as ſoon as ever they think they have an Opportunity, they enter upon Freſh Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies; and when they come at laſt to Suffer for their Crimes, ſcarce any ſort of Sinners ſeem to be more left to themſelves, and a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate Senſe, or may be generally<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to go out of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the World, with leſs Sign of any true Penitence. And I wiſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation had not been too<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> much verifi'd in the Behaviour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of thoſe Traytors, who Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for the late Conſpiracy.</p>
            <p>They ſhewed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> themſelves more Solicitous not to Diſcover their Accomplices, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers might ſtill have an Opportunity to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on the Work, which themſelves fail'd of, than about any great Sorrow for, or a Deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their own Crimes. And I could wiſh too, that moſt of our<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Diſſentors did not, both by their Talk and Behaviour, ſtill ſhew<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:64352:17"/> themſelves (as far as they dare) ſo much well-wiſhers to the accurſed Cauſe. But yet I hope that many, even of thoſe who have been deeply enough concerned in the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and would have been ready to have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of the thing, had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it Succeeded, will yet now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> take occaſion, from the ſo Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Defeat of the Horrid Deſign, to review thoſe accurſed Opinions and Principles, which moved them to be ſo much concerned; and ſo being more Senſible of their Duty, and Heartily ſorry for the Breach of it, become for the Future truly Loval and Obedient Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. By which means, the Defeated Wrath of our Adverſaries, will turn (as it Naturally tends) to God's Praiſe, and not a little to the Benefit of theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, Though all of the chief Actors, who know themſelves directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the Treaſon, ſhould ſtill (which God forbid) continue Obſtinate and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent; yet the Wrath of theſe Men will ſtill accidentally tend to God's Praiſe, and the good of the Church and Common-Wealth, in as much as the ſo clear Diſcovery and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the Conſpiracy muſt needs open the Eys of all Impartial and well-meaning
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64352:17"/> Men, who were before apt to entertain too good an Opinion, and ſubject to be drawn aſide with the fair pretences of theſe cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Incendiaries and Seducers. When once Honeſt Men come plainly to underſtand what they would be at, that under the pretence of Zeal for Religion, and God's<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Glory, they Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour nothing but Worldly Intereſt, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſs, and Cruelty, and make Liberty a meer Cloak for Maliciouſneſs, for Rapine, Treaſon, and Rebellion; they are then Sufficiently Antidoted and Secured againſt the Poiſonous Infuſions of their Deſtructive Principles. God has been pleaſed, once more, to Suffer theſe vile Hypocrites abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly to unmask themſelves; to proceed ſo far, as to ſhew their Wolves Teeth from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the covering of the Sheepskin, though they have not now been permitted to Bite. They have now ſo plainly diſcovered to the World their Bloudy Nature, that all Sincere hearted Perſons Will beware of ſuch falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and equally abhor their Practices, and the Curſed Principles which lead to them. Men will Suffer themſelves to be no more afrighted out of their Chriſtianity and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, into ſome of the worſt Errours of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64352:18"/> Popery, and into the immediate Danger of Perpetual Slavery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Confuſion, by the Mere Fears of Popery and Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Can any Man, who has the leaſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, himſelf, any longer believe theſe to be Men of tender Conſciences, who can thus ſtrain at a Gnat, and Swallow a Camel; that can ſtartle at the uſe of an Innocent Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony, and yet be ſo far from making the leaſt Scruple at the Horrid Murder of their moſt Gracious Prince, and the moſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Maſſacre<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of their Fellow-Subjects, that ever was Deſigned, as, on the contrary, to count it an Action moſt Heroick and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meritorious <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Muſt not he himſelf be perfectly out of his own Wats, who can any more be tempted to think, theſe Men and their Favourers, to be the only Sober, Godly party of the Nation, merely, becauſe they have the Modeſty to call themſelves ſo?</p>
            <p>After a Plot of this Horrid Complexion, ſo clearly Diſcovered, ſo Miraculouſly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated, a Plot, in which the whole Body of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters ſeem to have been, more or leſs, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd, &amp; which ſo Evidently proceeded from the Poiſon of Phanatical Principles; one would think<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the main Ring-leaders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhould now give
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64352:18"/> over of their own accord; &amp; that meer Shame and Deſpair (had they not long ago quite forgotten how to Bluſh) ſhould be Suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, without any other Law or Magiſtrate, to ſuppreſs their Seditious Conventicles, thoſe Schools of Hipocriſie and Rebellion; or, at leaſt, that they ſhould now be forced to give over the Trade, meenly for want of Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers. The Implacable Wrath and Villanous Attempts of theſe Men, have done enough to inlighten the Underſtandings, and open the Eyes of all Men, who have any; ſo that it now ſeems ſcarcely poſſible that any ſhould be longer deceived by them, who are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to deceive themſelves; their Fault can no longer be excuſed, by any ſuch thing as Ignorance: but muſt be Attributed to the moſt Affected Malice and Obſtinacy.</p>
            <p>Whilſt all Men who have any Senſe of Religion left in them, any Love to their King or Country, any Regard to the Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of their own Souls, or Bodys, will be careful to avoid the Maſters of ſuch Infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Aſſemblies; and returning again to the Boſom of the Church from which they have ſo wickedly departed, joyn with other Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Chriſtians, in the ſincere Worſhip of God,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64352:19"/> and in Honouring and Obeying of the King, and Live together with us in Peace, in Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Brotherly Love.</p>
            <p>Than which, what can tend more to the Praiſe of God, or the Benefit and Edification of the Church?</p>
            <p>And if any ſhall ſtill be ſo Stupidly weak, or Prodigiouſly Obſtinate, as to be willing to run after theſe Men, notwithſtanding all this; yet I hope, (which is the Third manner how their Wrath may tend to God's Praiſe) that the late Attempts of theſe Men, will Effectually awaken all Conſciencious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, in their ſeveral Places, to put thoſe wholſom Laws in Execution, which the Wiſdom of our Governours has long ſince provided in this Caſe. And I hope we are now better acquainted with things, and with the true meaning of both thoſe Words, than that any ſhould ſtill be afrighted from doing of their Duty, by the Odious Name of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution for Religion;</hi> by which, ſuch Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors have all along endeavoured to diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage Men's Charitable Diligence in this kind. We have formerly experienced, to our coſt, and have now again Learnt, with a Witneſs, what ſuch Men mean, by their Religion;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64352:19"/> under the Specious pretence of which, they are uſed to Meditate nothing elſe but Violence and Rapine, Murder and Rebellion; any juſt Penalty upon, or neceſſary reſtraint of them from the Commiſſion of which Crimes, they preſently call by the Name of <hi>Perſecution for Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They that would diſturb the Peace of a whole Nation, &amp; endeavour to take away the Life of their Lawful Sovereign, are certainly Guilty of a Crime, of a far higher Nature, than they who Commit a Common Felony or Murder upon a Pivate Man: and yet theſe latter uſually Suffer, without Pity; who (if they had but the ſame Impudence) might, with equal Right, pretend to Religion and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in the Caſe, and cry out of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion too. And why ſhould then the far great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Criminals be ſpared or Connived at, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for ſuch Impudent pretences, as indeed render them infinitely more Dangerous to the Common-Wealth, and more Juſtly A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable both to God and Man? Such a Religion as this, (if it muſt needs be cal'd ſo) the Devil himſelf is of; <hi>Who was a Murderer and a Lier from the Beginning.</hi> So that with what Face can ſuch Men ſay they are <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:64352:20"/> meerly becauſe they ate <hi>reſtrained from truly Perſecuting of others?</hi> whereas, for Magiſtrates not to endeavour to hinder them from this, by all Lawful Methods, would be indeed to Perſecute, and (in Effect) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the moſt Faithful Subjects of the Land, by giving theſe Men an Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to do ſo. And ſince our Schiſmatical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles have ever proved themſelves ſuch Schools of Hypocriſie and never-failing Seed-Plots of Sedition and Rebellion, 'tis truly an Act, no leſs of the higheſt Charity, than Juſtice (for all thoſe more immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by their Office) to endeavour, as they are Bound both by the Law of God and Man, and to uſe all due means, to ſuppreſs them. Which till it be Effectually done, in vain is it to hope for the leaſt quiet, or to ſee good days in <hi>England.</hi> Why ſhould Men, under the pretence of Religion, be Suffered to deſtroy it? Why ſhould they be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Poiſon the Minds of thoſe, who might otherwiſe prove good Subjects and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, with Principles of Sedition and Diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; to undo their Souls, and endanger the bringing of their Bodies to a ſhameful and untimely End; in a Word, to involve the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64352:20"/> whole Nation in Ruin and Confuſion, and to Propagate Schiſm, and lay the Foundation of Blood and Maſſacres to all Poſterity? Nor ſhall I be afraid to ſay, that we well Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, what Juncture of time it was, and by what kind of <hi>Repreſentatives,</hi> and are now alſo Senſible upon what deſign, it was voiced <hi>a thing greivous to the Subject to have Laws againſt Diſſenters put in Execution.</hi> Upon all which, and much more of the like Nature, the late Helliſh Conſpiracy has furniſhed us with ſuch a lively Comment, as may juſtly awaken Magiſtrates, to put thoſe very Laws in the moſt Vigorous Execution, as ever they deſire the Preſervation, either of the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Government now Eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>And let ſuch Men, who may thus <hi>Suffer as Evil Doors,</hi> cry out falſly of Perſecution, as much as they pleaſe; it is far better they ſhould do ſo, than all Honeſt Men feel their Perſecution indeed; Which can no ways, likely, be prevented, but by ſuch Timely and Legal Reſtraints of the Ring-leaders of the Faction.</p>
            <p>And if the Diſcovery of this Damnable Plot might (as well it may) have this good Effect, the Wrath of our Adverſaries would
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64352:21"/> (I make no Queſtion) very much tend to God's Praiſe, and the laſting Peace, and Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>But however, in the Fourth Place, This Plot muſt needs prove of no inconſiderable Advantage, in as much as it has enabled us moſt clearly to diſtinguiſh, betwixt Perſons; to know our True Friends from our Foes. It has been for the revealing of the Thoughts and Inclinations of many Mens Hearts; and hath Taught us Sufficiently both to diſcover and beware of a moſt Dangerous ſort of Enemies among us, becauſe Falſe, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous, and ſuch pretended Friends to the Church and State. Such Maſquerade Church of <hi>England</hi>-Men have now been Encouraged to caſt off their Viſards, and by their Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in all the late Seditious Tranſactions, have Sufficiently betray'd their Hollow-Heartedneſs, and how ready they are, upon all Occaſions, to warp, and (as one of them, who hath himſelf done ſo, Phraſeth it) to <hi>Play</hi> the Government <hi>a Slippery Trick.</hi> Theſe Men are ſo far only, of our Church, as may Enable them to do it more Miſcheif, than if they were it's. Profeſſed Enemies; and ſeem indeed, for no other End, willing to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64352:21"/> Communicate with us at all, but only to Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a better Opportunity thereby of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Deſtruction. And yet after they have joyned with the Diſſenters in all their ill Deſigns againſt the Government, and happen at laſt (any of them) together with the other, to be Diſcovered and Puniſhed for their Crime; the whole Body of the Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks endeavour preſently, from hence, to Acquit or Excuſe themſelves, by Impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhifting off the Reproach upon us; giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out that it is not ſo much a Plot of the Diſſenters, but ſuch in which thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> alſo have been, at leaſt, no leſs concerned.</p>
            <p>But, God be thanked, as ſuch Practices are wholy Inconſiſtent with our Principles, ſo Slander it ſelf has not, cannot pretend to taint any true Son of our Church, as the leaſt concerned in this Conſpiracy. They muſt needs own, that they were their own true Fellow-Proteſtants only, that were in it; not one Man of us, whom they wickedly call the Papiſts of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we have been at length ſurpriſed with a True and moſt Exceſſive <hi>Superlative,</hi> that has, all along, lain Lurking, even in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64352:22"/> thoſe who ſo much Pride themſelves with the Title of <hi>Moderate Men;</hi> and we are well aſſured that, in whatſoever elſe they may anſwer that Name, they have not done ſo, even in the loweſt and moſt <hi>Moderate</hi> degree (if any ſuch their could be) of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty. And it is ſome Comfort to conſider, that moſt others alſo of this Motley Tribe, who have not, perhaps, been directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in this Conſpiracy, have yet, by their greatly Favouring thoſe that were ſo, and by their other ill Behaviour towards the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in this Juncture, given ſuch Suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Indications of their Falſeneſs and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſincerity, that now all Men may eaſily ſee what they are; and our Governours both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical come plainly to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what kind of Snakes we have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Nouriſhed in our Boſoms.</p>
            <p>And certainly, as it is good that all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Men ſhould know one another; ſo is it more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſpecially Advantagious to the Phblick, for thoſe who are in Authority to be well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, what Perſons may ſafely be rely'd upon and encouraged, and who they are that can never be Oblig'd nor Truſted.</p>
            <p>But Fifthly and Laſtly, (which is indeed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64352:22"/> the more proper and immdiate work of the Day.) This Wrath of theirs does turn to God's Praiſe, as the Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and Prevention of ſo Horrid a Deſign Adminiſters a very Powerful Occaſion, to all Sincere Chriſtians, of Magnifying and Bleſſing God's Holy Name, and return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Poſſible Praiſe and Thanks for ſo Wonderful a Deliverance. As the Conſideration of this, may Juſtly move us to Admire and Adore God's Infinite Mercy and Goodneſs, his Faithfulneſs, Power, and the Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible Wiſdom of his Providence; <hi>Who diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Devices of the Crafty, ſo that their Hands can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not perform their enterprize; who taketh the Wiſe in their own Craftyneſs, ſo that the Counſel of the Forward is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Head-long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It Tends likewiſe to God's Praiſe, as the Conſideration of the ſame affords great Encouragement to all Faithful Perſons, of proceeding on Cheerfully in the Regular ways which they have choſen; of keeping cloſely to their Known Duty both towards God and Man; Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them likewiſe not to be Frighted out of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion or Loyalty, by the Lowd Clamours, Fears, or Threatnings of any unreaſonable Men in a Prevaling Faction: but to rely firmly upon God's good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in the Faithful diſcharge of their Duty; we hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, from hence, a Senſible Experiment and Example, how both able and willing God is to preſerve the Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ready, in his Good time, utterly to confound all the Machinations of Wicked Men againſt them; ſo that there is no Preſervative like to that of Integrity, <hi>and he that walketh uprightly, walketh ſurely.</hi> To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, it muſt needs much promote God's Glory, as the Conſideration of it will Effectually move, all well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Perſons among us, to expreſs their Thankfulneſs to God, for ſo great a Deliverance, by Seriouſly endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64352:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> to walk anſwerably to the Mercy; by duly Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Lives, and ordering their Converſations aright, and firmly reſolving upon a more ſtrict Obedience in all the Holy Laws of ſo Gracious, ſo Faithful and Bountiful Maſter.</p>
            <p>This, this is the true Praiſe, the Genuine Fruit which God expects from us, and the particular Mercy ſo lowd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly calls for at our Hands; and without which indeed, we are delivered but to little purpoſe. But if we uſe our beſt Care, to let it have this due Effect upon our Hearts and Lives, we may then be moſt confident that the ſame God, who has been now our Rock and Defence, and mighty Salvation, will ſtill be ſo. If their Defeated Wrath prove but thus to Gods Praiſe, in us; we need not in the leaſt Queſtion, but that he who has, and does, will ſtill deliver us. And let the ſame, or any other Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, continue to Plot, what they can, for our Ruin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let them ſtill bear never ſo Tyrannous a Hate againſt us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet the great Governour of the World will not fail to blaſt all their<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Deſigns, <hi>and the Remainder of their Wrath</hi> moſt certainly <hi>Reſtrain.</hi> Which God Grant of his Infinte Mercy, Through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Lord,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 4. lin. 2. make (;) for (?) p. 9. 1. 6. after <hi>it</hi> make (,) p. 9. laſt line but two, after <hi>duty</hi> make (?) p. 18. 1. 13. for <hi>in Rage</hi> read <hi>outrage</hi> p. 37. l. 18. for <hi>doors</hi> read <hi>doers.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
